"Do Not Eat Pawpaws"
The pawpaw
is the largest fruit
native to North America,
weighing up
to two pounds (1 kg).
Look at these beauties!
You can just
scoop it right out.
Pawpaws taste like
a mixture of bananas,
mangos, and pineapples.
They're like a tropical
banana-mango custard,
but found in
temperate forests
across the eastern
United States,
nourishing humankind
for thousands of years
and now complete with
their own pawpaw festivals.
Papayas are
sometimes called pawpaws,
but they're
completely different fruits.
The real pawpaw is
also known as the dog banana,
false-banana,
Indian banana,
prairie banana,
poor man's banana,
Ozark banana,
Banango (I like that one),
Indiana banana
(has a nice ring to it, too),
and the Kentucky banana.
Pawpaws are my
favorite fruit,
or, should I say,
were my favorite fruit.
One of the reasons
that I moved to rural Virginia
was because the property
had a whole grove
of pawpaw trees.
I was going to be
set for life.
That is, until I ate
a few too many
on the first harvest,
became quite ill,
and actually looked them up.
Pro tip: in the future,
look to see if a food is toxic
before you eat lots of it.
Little did I know,
the pawpaw belonged
to an infamous
family of fruits
that contain three different
types of neurotoxins.
I had actually done
a video, years ago,
warning people
not to eat soursop,
also known as graviola,
but didn't realize
pawpaws were related.
The family includes
soursop, guanabana, sweetsop,
sugar apple, cherimoya,
and custard-apple,
which are all linked to
a neurodegenerative disease
called progressive
supranuclear palsy,
which is like a
treatment-resistant Parkinson's,
with hallucinations,
widespread brain atrophy,
and dementia.
And consumption
of these fruits
is associated with
about 20 times the odds
of having this kind of
atypical Parkinson's syndrome.
Expose rats to even
a fraction of the dose
the people were exposed to,
and they develop the same
kind of brain lesions
you see on autopsy
in human victims.
And, in several patients who
stopped consuming these fruits,
the progression
of their condition ceased,
and, in one patient,
the symptoms even disappeared
after a change in diet.
There is an urgent need
to raise public awareness
about the neurotoxicity
of this family of fruits,
which are often,
ironically, praised
for their taste
and medicinal values.
In fact, you can find
dietary supplements
containing these plants,
promoted for their
purported anticancer effects.
And a soursop extract
can inhibit cancer cell growth
in a petri dish,
but only at concentrations
much higher than the amount
that kills off brain cells.
Even a low
cumulative consumption
may worsen disease severity
and cognitive deficits
in degenerative
Parkinson's type disease,
as in 0.2 fruit-years.
So, that's just one-fifth
of a fruit a day for a year,
or a single fruit a month
for six years,
or just one fruit a year
throughout your entire life.
The bottom line
is that these fruit
could contribute
to the development
of degenerative
parkinsonism in humans,
and so, as a precaution,
more restrictive public health
preventive recommendations
should be made
regarding their consumption.
So, okay, consumption
of these tropical fruits
potentially constitutes
a serious public health problem,
but what about pawpaws?
Here's the amount
of the primary neurotoxin
in soursop, aka graviola.
Pawpaws have ten times more.
So, why aren't
pawpaw eaters getting sick?
Well, it's only ripe
for a few weeks a year,
so, unlike the tropical fruit
that can be eaten year-round,
people may not have
a lot of exposure to them.
Fresh pawpaws aren't really
even sold commercially, either,
since they bruise so easily,
but now the fruit's
available in any season,
sold as frozen pulp or jam,
and there are
supplements out there too.
Not to mention,
if you're like me,
trees in your backyard.
When the U.S. Food and Drug
Administration was asked about them,
they noted that pawpaw
has a long history of food use,
and it didn't have any evidence
that the fruit was unsafe to eat.
You'll hear things like this:
"Currently,
there have been no reports
of neurogenerative diseases
linked to the consumption
of the pawpaw fruit,"
until, of course, there are.
"Progressive supranuclear
palsy and pawpaw."
Poor guy had trouble
speaking and walking
as his brain
was atrophying in his skull.
Tragically he actually died
before they figured it out,
but his wife disclosed
that they owned pawpaw trees,
and he had been
eating dozens a year.
And when researchers
started looking,
they indeed seemed
to find a link between
this neurodegenerative disease
and pawpaw consumption
in the United States.
So, alas,
no more pawpaws for me.